Guide to the James H. Moser Collection 1883-2009 MS 022 MS 022 MS 022
Cornwall Historical Society
James Henry Moser Collection
1883-2009
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS 022
1 linear feet (2 boxes)
This collection contains items related to artist James Henry Moser (1854-1913).
Provenance
This collection was begun by local historian E.C. Starr, and expanded by later members of the Cornwall Historical Society like Paula Holmes and Michael Gannett.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Moser was born in Whitby, Ontario, Canada in 1854. After studying with landscape painters John C. Whitt and Charles H. David, he moved to Toledo, Ohio where he opened his own studio. In 1877, Moser began teaching art classes in Toledo to help generate extra income. One of his students was Martha Scoville () of Cornwall, who was in Ohio visiting extended family. Moser soon proposed to her, but she returned to her hometown without answering definitively.
In 1881, Moser found widespread recognition after he agreed to illustrate Joel Chandler Harris’ bestseller, Uncle Remus, His Songs and His Sayings. During this time, he frequently visited Martha at her family’s farm in Cornwall, and she accepted his proposal in 1883.The couple soon moved to Atlanta, and then Washington, D.C. in 1887. In addition to painting, Moser wrote a column for the Washington Post and taught an art class at the Corcoran School of Art from 1898-1913. Moser’s work was much praised during his lifetime, and he was the recipient of a medal at the 1895 Atlanta Exposition, the first Corcoran Prize in 1900, and the Parsons Prize in 1903. Although he painted in a variety of mediums, he was best known for his watercolors and his landscape paintings.
Near the Scoville farm, Moser and his family built a vacation cottage on Cream Hill, and painted many of his landscapes in Cornwall. He died of a stroke in 1913 in Washington, D.C., and was buried in the North Cornwall Cemetery.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes Moser’s personal items, as well as documents related to past exhibits in Cornwall on the artist. I
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading then chronologically within each subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Personal Papers
Publications
Artwork
Cornwall Historical Society Materials
Manuscripts
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Artists.; Cornwall (Conn.); Articles; Correspondence; leaflets; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Moser, James Henry, 1854-1913.
- Personal Papers
  - Copy of Moser-Scoville wedding announcement, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter sent from J. H. Moser to E.C. Starr, regarding Law and Order League, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter sent from J.H. Moser to Hubert Pratt, regarding life in Washington, D.C., 1897 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Program for “Washington Watercolor Club” exhibition, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter sent from J.H. Moser to Mr. Calhoun, regarding donated paintings, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notice regarding praise of Moser’s work, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invitation to Corcoran School award ceremony, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sign for J.H. Moser’s studio, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photograph of Mr. Ruland, who was painted by Moser in 1906, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Publications
  - Printer illustration of William Ewart Gladstone by J.H. Moser, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Articles by J.H. Moser, 1900-1908, undated (Box 1, Folder 26-Nov)
  - Memorial items, 1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 27-30)
- Artwork
  - “Philadelphia Water Color Exhibition” catalogue, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Copy for Water-Color Club exhibition of Moser’s work, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Copy of Woodward Lothrop catalogue of Moser’s works, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Catalogue of Douglas Galleries, auctioneers, collection of Moser works, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Invitations to Moser exhibitions, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - List of watercolors by Moser exhibited by V. G. Fischer Art Gallery, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - List of connoisseurs of Moser’s art, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Labeled photographs of Moser paintings taken by Moser descendant James M. Fetherolf, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Thinking Man, 1890-2 (Object item 009)
  - The Bookworm, 1890 (Object The Bookworm)
  - Windmill by Sea (Object item 049)
  - Fall Foliage (Object item 102)
  - Produce Tent (Object item 085)
  - Pond's Edge (Object Item 069)
  - Sunset Over the Hills (Object item 063)
  - Portico (Object item 105)
  - Man with Corn Stalk, Tennessee 1883 (Object item 013)
- Cornwall Historical Society Items
  - Letter and two Moser pencil drawings of Cornwall sent to Michael Gannett from Grace Moser Fetherolf, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence of Cornwall Historical Society regarding the general use and locations of Moser artwork, 1968-2008; , undated (Box 1, Folder 40-56)
  - Items related to 1974 exhibit (Box 1, Folder 57-60)
  - Items related to 1983 exhibit (Box 1, Folder 61-63)
  - Program for 1992 exhibit (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Reactions to Moser exhibit, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Biographical information, undated (Box 1, Folder 66-67)
  - Information on Moser-Scoville connection, by Ginny Potter, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - List of Moser paintings and their locations, undated (Box 1, Folder 69-70)
  - Memo of Moser acquisitions by historical society, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Miscellaneous
  - Account of former slave, “Old Hen,” the inspiration of several Moser works, by Ralph Scoville, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Program for Cornwall Free Library exhibit on Moser, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 73)
- Manuscripts
  - Thesis, “The Landscapes of James Henry Moser,” by Rosemary A. Breen, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - List of unpublished manuscript material, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - “James Henry Moser, His Brush and His Pen,” by Grace Moser Fetherolf, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Album of Moser’s paintings, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)